<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham, in the Isle of Ree Containing these particulars. The manner of releeuing the fort by sixe shallops about a moneth since. The now state of the fort, with the taking of some of the gouernours messengers who were swimming to the maine with letters, and were afterwards executed. The comming of the French Kings brother before Rochel, with the building of a new fort. A sally made by the Rochellers vpon the French, where many of the French were slaine. The great preparation of the King of France, the King of Spaine, and the Arch-Dutches, to releeue the fort with 60. sayle of ships. The death of Sir Iohn Burrowes. The death of the Gouernour Thorax his brother, who was slaine that night. ... With many other particulars. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838805</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3194</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1159:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham, in the Isle of Ree Containing these particulars. The manner of releeuing the fort by sixe shallops about a moneth since. The now state of the fort, with the taking of some of the gouernours messengers who were swimming to the maine with letters, and were afterwards executed. The comming of the French Kings brother before Rochel, with the building of a new fort. A sally made by the Rochellers vpon the French, where many of the French were slaine. The great preparation of the King of France, the King of Spaine, and the Arch-Dutches, to releeue the fort with 60. sayle of ships. The death of Sir Iohn Burrowes. The death of the Gouernour Thorax his brother, who was slaine that night. ... With many other particulars. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 9, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Eagle and Childe in Britaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: October 2.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24743a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears two woodcuts of ships, rotated 90⁰; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>First leaf lacking.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1592-1628.</term>
               <term>Ré Expedition, 1627 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>ships and smiling fish scene</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Continued <hi>October</hi> 2. IOVRNALL Of all the Proceedings of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ree.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Containing theſe particulars.</head>
               <item>The manner of releeuing the Fort by ſixe Shallops about a moneth ſince.</item>
               <item>The now ſtate of the Fort, with the taking of ſome of the Gouernours Meſſengers who were ſwimming to the Maine with Letters, and were afterwards executed.</item>
               <item>The comming of the French Kings brother before <hi>Rochel,</hi> with the building of a new Fort.</item>
               <item>A ſally made by the <hi>Rochellers</hi> vpon the French, where many of the French were ſlaine.</item>
               <item>The great preparation of the King of <hi>France,</hi> the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Arch-Dutches,</hi> to releeue the Fort with 60. ſayle of Ships.</item>
               <item>The death of Sir <hi>Iohn Burrowes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The death of the Gouernour <hi>Thorax</hi> his Brother, who was ſlaine that night.</item>
               <item>An attempt of the French, with 12. Barkes to releeue the Fort, where of ſixe were taken.</item>
               <item>A meſſage ſent from the Gouernour Monſieur <hi>Thorax</hi> to the Duke, and the ſucceſſe thereof.</item>
               <item>The killing of two French men in their owne trenches, by an Iriſh Souldier.</item>
            </list>
            <p>With many other particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Walkley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Eagle</hi> and <hi>Childe</hi> in <hi>Britaines Burſſe.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3194:3"/>
            <head>THE IOVRNALL CONTINVED TO <hi>THIS DAY.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Continued to the <hi>2.</hi> of October.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Army vnder the Conduct of his Illuſtrious Excellency, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> lyes as yet before the Fort of Saint <hi>Martins</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Ree,</hi> which they haue intrenched round about, except vpon the North ſide where it is enuironed with the Sea, yet that paſſage is ſo blockt vp by our Ships, Pinnaces, and Long boates, that it is a matter difficult, if not altogether impoſſible, (as matters ſtands now) to put any Prouiſion of Victualls into the <hi>Citadell.</hi> For ſince that ſixe Shalloppes of the Enemies, about a moneth ſince, brought ſome reliefe (though ſmall to the beſiedged) by the benefit of a ſeaſonable night, and by the conniuence (as it was doubted) of ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> who came to the Iland for Salt, and lay betwixt vs and the maine. But now all hope of ſuccour is debarred that way, by running two of our warlike Ships on ground, cloſe vnder the Fort,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3194:4"/>vpon the Auenue of the water Port, and by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and vigilancy of the reſt of the Fleete, who leaue no courſe vnattempted, which Art or induſtry can propoſe for the finiſhing of this great worke, vpon which the honour of our Nation liyes ſo much ingaged.</p>
            <p>So that beſides the ordinary night and day wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches obſerued carefully by the Sea-men, diuerſe long Boates well furniſhed with Musketiers and Marriners round it about the Iſland all the night long, who haue intercepted three French Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Fort, that by ſwimming thought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the maine with the Gouernours Letters</p>
            <p>The Contents of theſe Letters implied: <hi>That their want within were great, that the Soldiers began to Mutenie, and that without ſpeedy reliefe they could hold out no longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Meſſengers who ſought to conuay them being apprehended, were hanged in ſight of the Fort, with the Letters about their neckes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the importunity of theſe aduertiſements want cauſe, for as it appeareth by the teſtimonie of diuers fugitiues, and by the euidence of ſundry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable circumſtances, the beſieged are ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed for want of neceſſaries, that although their Infantery be of the Regiment of <hi>Champaigne</hi> (which is held to bee one of the braueſt of all <hi>France</hi>) and though there are diuers reſolute Caualiers within it (the reliques of thoſe troupes, which at their firſt landing, were defeated by the Engliſh) yet want begins to make them looſe both courage and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and to demeane themſelues in a mutinous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3194:4"/>and inſolent manner towards the Gouernour, who knowing well the truth and iuſtice of their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, giues them good words, and bids them be confident of ſuddaine reliefe. But wordes and winde feedes not the belly, as honour heates not the toes: ſo that their diſcontents remaine as great as their necsſſities are preſsing. The violent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement whereof makes them ruune away by troupes ten and twenty in a company, and cauſeth others to aduenture themſelues deſperately out of their Workes, to gather Grapes, which growe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Fort, and our approches, many of whom are fetcht off by our Muskatiers, and ſlaine with the meate ſticking in their mouthes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe within are allowed a ſmall proportion of horſefleſh, and ſixe and fifty Peas a day.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France</hi> his Brother is come downe within a league of <hi>Rochell,</hi> with an Army of 11. thouſand ſtrong, both Horſe and Foote: he brings ſixe braſſe Peeces with him from <hi>Paris,</hi> with great ſtore of Munition, and ſundry materialls fit for the building of a Fort, the foundation whereof the French haue already layd oppoſite vnto that Fort, which was built on the North-Weſt ſide of the Towne, in the yeare 1522. yet the <hi>Rochellers</hi> being confident of their owne ſtrength, and of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſuccours (which are ready to aſsiſt them vpon all occaſions) reſolue to endure all extreames, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to put their neckes vnder the yoake, or to faile in the courſe of their former reſolutions.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of <hi>Rochell,</hi> the Enemies lying neere, ſent out twenty common Souldiers on horſeback cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3194:5"/>in ſcarlet coates, and Armed after the manner of the French Gentlemen. The ſhew of this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſalley, cauſed ſome principall Caualiers of the Kings ſide to iſſue out of their Workes, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to encounter them. But they retiring, and the others purſuing, they fell into an Ambuſh of 50. Muskatiers purpoſely layd by the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> where diuers of them were ſlaine, amongſt whom were two men of quality: for the recouering of one of whoſe bodies there happened a great Conflict, in which diuers of the French were ſlaughtered.</p>
            <p>Although the ground about the Fort be hard to worke in, yet all difficulties being ſurmounted, our men haue drawne their approaches from the maine intrenchment (which lyes betweene Saint <hi>Martins</hi> Towne and the Fort) within leſſe then Piſtoll ſhot of the vtmoſt Counterskarfe, and that vpon two ſeuerall wayes or Auenues, whereof one is directed from the Batterie, and the other from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt.</p>
            <p>Our Cannoniers haue diſmounted all their Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, except two ſling Peeces, but of theſe they are able to make little vſe, for want of Bullets: in foureteene dayes they haue made but one great Shot vpon our Quarter, which was but an exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Bullet, ſhot firſt from one of our Peeces.</p>
            <p>But to ſupply this defect (though with a feeble meanes) they ſhoote and throwe many ſtones from their Workes, with which our men are ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, that it cauſeth as little terrour as it doth danger.</p>
            <p>Our Armie keepes quatter with the French on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3194:5"/>land, for all thoſe who are taken priſoners, or run out of the Fort, after a daies reſtraint or two are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, and ſent into the maine with meanes of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation &amp; conduct. But of late no quarter is kept with them who are aken at Sea, becauſe it appeared by the confeſsion of ſome who were taken by our Boates vpon the 19. of the laſt moneth, that they are to confident and preſumtiue vpon the Dukes mercie. His Excellencie lyeth in the Towne of Saint <hi>Martins,</hi> not farre from the Market place, attentiuely watching all faire opportunities, whoſe care and vigilancie wee hope that God will bleſſe with good ſucceſſe. Monſieur <hi>Subuiſa</hi> is in the Towne of <hi>Rochell,</hi> to confirme the Inhabitants with his preſence and counſell.</p>
            <p>The beſieged haue not beene ſſacke in their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for beſides their continuall plying vs with their vollyes of great and ſmall ſhot, they haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vndermine one of our Batteries, but this Deſigne of theirs was fruſtrated by a Countermine of ours, which wrought ſuch effects, that they were beaten out of their own Mine after ſome reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>They are ſo much diſtreſſed for want of ſhotte, that wanting Lead and Iron, they are faine to melt all their Pewter and Tinne, of which they make Bullets. But this ſhot ſhatters like Hayle, and doth leſſe hurt by farre then the other.</p>
            <p>His Excellence is very ſparing of his men, as well knowing that walles of bones are farre ſtronger then thoſe of earth and ſtones, and reſolues by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the preſident of <hi>Vanden Berke</hi> at <hi>Gulicke,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3194:6"/>and of <hi>Spinola</hi> at <hi>Breda</hi> to ſtarne the beſieged, or elſe to bring them to reaſon.</p>
            <p>Vpon the Intercourſe of ſome meſſages, his Grace hath imployed Mr. <hi>Aiſhburnham</hi> (a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his, lately arriued in <hi>England</hi>) vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſpeciall buſineſſe, twice or thrice vnto the Gouernour <hi>Thorax.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon his comming to the vtmoſt Sentinell, and the remonſtrance of his imployment, his eyes were blindfolded, and in this manner (becauſe hee ſhould not diſcouer their Workes) he was conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receiue his audience.</p>
            <p>The French giue out, that if wee doe not depart the ſooner, they will cauſe vs to doe it by maine force, being confident of thoſe aydes which are promiſed them from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Archdutcheſſe, which together with their owne Ships, will make a Fleete of threeſcore ſaile, as they reckon in their large account. But I thinke this bragging of theirs will turne meerely into a French vapour, much ſhewe and little action. Howſoeuer they are ſure to find a ſtout oppoſition, and a braue reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Courtney,</hi> a Souldier of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and experience, and Colonell of one of the Engliſh Regiments, was ſhot with a Musket from the Fort vpon the belly, but the Buller lighting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome money in a little pocket, loſt his force, and did no farther hurt.</p>
            <p>Vpon Wedneſday being the twelfth of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that Honourable and valiant Knight Sir <hi>Iohn
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3194:6"/>Burrowes,</hi> Colonell Generall of the Engliſh Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie vnder his Excellencie the Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> being carefull for the direction and ſuruay of all our Workes, came vp from his Quarters in the after-noone, to giue orders for the lniing out of a new Intrenchment, and as hee came off from the Workes with ſome other Commanders, hee was vnfortunately ſhot in the belly thorow the guttes, about fiue of the clocke in the euening, with a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, which wound proued mortall: for within foure or fiue houres after he gaue vp the ghoſt, to the exceeding griefe of all the Armie, but ſpecially of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who comming to viſite him before his death, ſhed many paſsionate teares to expreſſe his griefe, due to the remembrance of ſo worthy a perſon. Hee ſhewed a great deale of conſtancie, reſolution, &amp; religion at his death, as he had in the whole courſe and paſſage of his life. His body was opened and enbalmed, and ſent into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with Mr, <hi>Aiſhburnham,</hi> who brought it to <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> on Monday, being the 24. of September, from whence it is comming about to <hi>Poteſmouth,</hi> to be tranſported thence vnto <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where it is to receiue the Sepulchrall rites of an Honorable interment.</p>
            <p>Our Souldiers, but eſpecially thoſe of his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were ſo much prouoked with this vnexpected accident, that in reuenge thereof they powred di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers vollyes of ſmall &amp; great ſhot vpon the French, with the ſtorme whereof the Gouernours brother was ſlaine, and ſome other men of quality.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3194:7"/>
            <p>On the Wedneſday following Sir <hi>Iohn Burrowes</hi> death, the French from the maine ſought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Fort with twelue Barkes laden with vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals and Muni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, but they were intercepted by our ſea Watch, and ſixe of them taken, and all the Victualls and Prouiſion brought in to our Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin; the other fixe were driuen backe vnto the Maine, but if the other Shallops that got in before, were no better ſtored then theſe, as in all likelihood they were not, there was not Victuals enough to ſerue them 14 dayes.</p>
            <p>The Priſoners being demaunded how they durſt hazard themſelues ſo boldly vpon this attempt, anſwered, that they did it vpon confidence of the Dukes mercy, which they thought would not faile them if they were ſurprized. But to preuent this, and to hinder the like preſumption, in others our Souldiers put them all to the ſword, before they receiued any other orders from his Excellencie.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Thorax</hi> the Gouernour of the Fort, ſent to his Excellence the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> to intreat him to giue leaue that he might ſend a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to his Maſter the French King, which was granted by his Excellence, vpon condition that he would vndertake that hee might ſend a ſeruant of his ſafely thorough <hi>France</hi> for <hi>England:</hi> this being agreed on both ſides, his Excellence diſpatched Maſter <hi>Aſhburneham,</hi> a Gentleman of his Chamber, to goe along with the Gouernours ſeruant; but when they came to <hi>Paris,</hi> the French neuer reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the noble fauour done vnto them by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3194:7"/>but contrary to all expectation, would not giue leaue that Mr. <hi>Aiſhburneham</hi> ſhould paſſe any further, but to returne backe to the Iland: the Gouernours man that came backe with him, his Excellence cauſed all his Letters to be taken from him, and keepeth him priſoner in the Armie.</p>
            <p>The 2600. Engliſh and Iriſh vnder the command of Sir <hi>Ralph Bingley,</hi> and Sir <hi>Pierce Croſſeby,</hi> are ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued ſafely in the Iland: ſince whoſe comming there happened a memorable accident, by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of two Souldiers of thoſe troupes: who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vp into our approaches, went from thence ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly into the Enemies trenches, lying cloſe vnto our Workes, where they being diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by the French Sentinell <hi>Perdieu,</hi> hee ſhot one of them dead with his Musket. The ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuing Iriſh-man to reuenge his Fellowes death, drew out his skeane, and ſlew the French man, and being ſhot at (but miſt) by another French Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katier, hee killed him likewiſe, and leaping out of the Trenches, into which hee had ingaged himſelfe vnaduiſedly, hee came off cleare, and without any hurt at all.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the Journall.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:8"/>
            <head>Vpon the death of that noble Knight, Sir <hi>Iohn Burrowes.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F honour, vertue, and the glorious face</l>
            <l>Of noble actions could prolong the race</l>
            <l>Of mans appointed dayes, then had thy Fate</l>
            <l>Not made the Court and Campe diſconſolate</l>
            <l>Renowned <hi>Burrowes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Iohn Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes</hi> got much honour at the ſiege of <hi>Oſtend</hi> and <hi>Frankendale,</hi> and at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Bell Sconce</hi> by the <hi>Buſſe,</hi> where the Marqueſſe of <hi>Beluille,</hi> a braue Italian Colonell was ſlaine.</note> then <hi>Oſtendes</hi> report,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Frankendales</hi> laſt ſiege, and that ſurpriſed Fort</l>
            <l>Where <hi>Beluilles</hi> Marqueſſe fell, had ſtopt the Knife</l>
            <l>Of fatall <hi>Atropos,</hi> and made thy life</l>
            <l>Immortall like thy actions: but no merit</l>
            <l>Which liues within mans beſt deſeruing ſpirit</l>
            <l>Can repeale Deaths decrees, for all muſt die,</l>
            <l>Slaine by the Shafts of dire mortality.</l>
            <l>Thus did the Funerall pile great <hi>Pompey</hi> burne,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Caeſars</hi> corpes fill'd the ſepulchrall Vrne.</l>
            <l>And thus braue <hi>Burrowes</hi> ſleepes in Honours bed,</l>
            <l>Who dying liues, intomb'd, vnburied;</l>
            <l>Worthy Foes worth to haue ſuruiu'd that death,</l>
            <l>Which robb'd him of his valour breathing breath.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:3194:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
